Guide to the Duke Family New York Apartments Collection, 1908-1997 RL.01435
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Family New York Apartments collection
1908-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke family
RL.01435
2.6 Linear Feet
J.B. Duke acquired a lot on the northeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 78th Street and commissioned Horace Trumbauer to draw the plans for a new residence in 1909. It was in this mansion that his daughter Doris was born and raised. After J.B.'s death in 1925, Nanaline continued to live in the mansion until January, 1958 when she and Doris donated the house to New York University's Institute of Fine Arts. Throughout her adulthood Doris continued to live in New York City, residing in a penthouse located at 3 E. 84th Street and a penthouse at 475 Park Avenue, which was her last New York City residence when she died in 1993. The collection primarily documents the expenses and daily operations of running and maintaining three large residences in New York City. Materials include invoices and receipts for repairs and renovations to the residences, correspondence and memoranda relating to routine matters of the residences including expenses, inventories of furniture, fixtures, and other household items, and appraisals of the residences and their household effects. A majority of the architectural records in this collection are related to the design and construction of J.B. Duke's mansion at 1 E. 78th Street.
approx. 1,200 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Digital use copies in this collection have been migrated to a library server and can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access please contact Research Services prior to visiting the library.
Provenance
Materials in the Duke Family New York Apartments Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
Although James B. Duke preferred his countryside residence of Duke Farms (located in the township of Hillsborough, New Jersey) to that of a bustling metropolis, the newly married Mrs. J.B. (Nanaline) Duke enjoyed the many social aspects of living in New York City. As such, J.B. acquired a lot on the northeast corner of Fifth Avenue and 78th Street and commissioned Horace Trumbauer to draw plans for the new residence in 1909. It was in this mansion that his daughter Doris was born and raised. After J.B.'s death in 1925, Nanaline continued to live in the mansion until January, 1958 when she and Doris donated the house to New York University's Institute of Fine Arts. Throughout her adulthood Doris continued to live in New York City (oftentimes splitting her time between New York and her several other homes), residing in a penthouse located at 3 E. 84th Street and a penthouse at 475 Park Avenue, which was her last New York City residence when she died in 1993.
Collection Overview
The Duke Family New York Apartments Collection (formerly NYM, NYA84, and NYA) is part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. This collection consists of three record groups that were intentionally assembled due to the similarity of the subject. The collection spans the years 1908 to 1997, beginning with the design and construction of James B. Duke's mansion at 1 E. 78th Street and ending with the maintenance and general upkeep of Doris Duke's 475 Park Avenue apartment after her death. The collection is arranged in three series by purchase date: New York Mansion (1 E. 78th Street), New York Apartment (3 E. 84th Street, Penthouse), and New York Apartment (475 Park Avenue, Penthouse B). Each of the series has an Administrative Records sub series; however the New York Mansion and 475 Park Avenue Penthouse both have an Architectural Records sub series. The collection primarily documents the expenses and daily operations of running and maintaining three large residences in New York City. Administrative records for all three series generally include invoices and receipts for repairs and renovations to the residences, correspondence and memoranda relating to routine matters of the residences including expenses, inventories of furniture, fixtures, and other household items, and appraisals of the residences and their household effects. A majority of the architectural records in this collection are related to the design and construction of J.B. Duke's mansion at 1 E. 78th Street. The materials in this collection are arranged loosely in chronological order.
Related Material
James Buchanan Duke Papers, 1777-1990
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Family Papers, 1885-1992
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Architecture -- Designs and plans; New York (N.Y.); Architectural drawing -- New York (State); Duke, Doris; Trumbauer, Horace, 1869-1938; New York City. Institute of Fine Arts; Duke family; Duke family; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925
- New York Mansion (1 E. 78th Street), 1908-1975
  Scope and Contents note
  Completed in 1912, the 32-room house at the northeast corner of 78th Street and Fifth Avenue was designed by architect Horace Trumbauer. The 40,000 square foot, five story granite and limestone house was said to have been originally modeled after the Hotel Labottiere, a Bordeaux townhouse constructed in the 18th century. In a December, 1957 appraisal of the house (appraised at $1.85 million) it was described as "probably the finest of the old elegant mansion type houses built in New York City." In January, 1958 Doris Duke and her mother Nanaline donated the house to New York University's Institute of Fine Arts, where it was to be named the James B. Duke House. At the time, the house was worth an estimated $1.6 million.
  - Administrative Records, 1908-1975
    Material in this sub series consists of invoices and purchases for the mansion on 1 E. 78th Street including furniture, fixtures, groceries and other household items, and several appraisals of "household effects" and the house itself, completed during different years. Also included in this series are agreements and correspondence between New York University (NYU) and The Doris Duke Foundation for the donation of the house and other monetary gifts to NYU and the overall closing of the house.
    - Stationary for the New York Mansion, 1 E. 78th St. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, notes, and related materials concerning Doris Duke’s donations to N.Y.U.’s Institute of Fine Arts (IFA) including furniture and items on loan, and the donation of tapestries to Duke University and the N.C. State Art Society. Includes inventories of silver, china, etc. sent to Somerville from 1 E. 78th St. and a partial list of furnishings (1914). 1914, 1956-1957, 1959–1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence relating to a variety of topics affecting the 1 E. 78th St. house including tapestries, donations, and the overall closing of the house by May 31, 1956. 1956–1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence relating to the Doris Duke Foundation’s annual gift of $12,000 to N.Y.U.’s Institute of Fine Arts. Gifts were in addition to the $100,000 gift to the Institute for renovations in 1958. 1958–1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Receipts and related materials concerning J.B. Duke’s rug purchases 1908, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Receipts, silver, for 1 E. 78th St. purchased by J.B. Duke. 1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statement of groceries purchased for 1 E. 78th St. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Statements and invoices for purchases made by Mrs. James B. Duke. 1916, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Invoices for furniture and fixtures purchased for 1 E. 78th St. 1935–1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Invoices for musical instruments purchased by Doris Duke. 1935–1942, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Invoices for candle holders purchased for 1 E. 78th St. 1936, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Invoices for lighting including chandeliers, lamps, and shades purchased for 1 E. 78th St. and lighting work completed in the Ball Room and Main Hall. 1936–1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Invoice and voucher for antique textiles from Alice Baldwin Beer, antique textiles, and Lanishi Lall and Son, Agra, India. January 1939, March 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Estimates of proposed work at 1 E. 78th St. by McMillen, Inc. 1940–1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Invoice for 7 cut stem glasses from Alice Syndam antique silver and porcelain dealer. September 1, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Invoices for dinnerware and glassware at 1 E. 78th St. 1942–1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Invoice and related correspondence concerning roofing work at 1 E. 78th St. for Nanaline Duke. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Invoices and vouchers for reupholstery work performed on chairs at the New York Mansion. Includes invoices for reupholstery work done for the New York Apartment, Rough Point, and Duke Farms. 1959, 1964–1965, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Appraisal of house at 1 E. 78th St. and 5th Avenue. House appraised at $1,850,000.00. December 10, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Agreement between New York University and The Doris Duke Foundation for a gift of $100,000 to the University to help defray expenses during renovation of 1 E. 78th St. January 24, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Satisfaction of Mortgage Contract and related legal correspondence in connection with Doris Duke’s donation of 14 E. 78th St. to N.Y.U. 1964–1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Appraisal of Furnishings of the Residence of J.B. Duke at 1 E. 78th St. Executed by Continental Appraisal Co., N.Y. February 4, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Institute of Fine Arts News (school newspaper of New York University) highlighting James B. Duke House, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Booklet, The Institute of Fine Arts, New York University, given to Doris Duke, 1963 Spring (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - New York – Inventory of Furniture & Equipment. 1918–1925 (Box 2)
    - Appraisal, Household effects, 1 E. 78th St. 1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Inventory, 1 E. 78th St. (mostly), copies, compiled on May 28, 1988. Receipts. 1940s–1980s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Appraisal of tapestries located at 1 E. 78th St. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - List of Household Articles, Ornaments, Etc., Furniture in Sitting-Room and Bedroom (Doris Duke) and Linens, 1 E. 78th St. October 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Street plan of E. 78th, E. 79th, Madison, and Fifth Avenue. March 2, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Architectural Records, 1909-1910, 1958 and undated
    About 75 items
    Includes blueprints, lithographs, pencil, ink, and crayon drawings, and Vandyke prints detailing the design and renovations to J.B. Duke's mansion located on 1 E. 78th Street in New York City. A majority of the drawings date from July 1909 and include drafts and revisions to floor plans, elevations, interior rooms and notes on materials (e.g., Indiana limestone, granite). Several of the blueprints are signed by J.B. Duke including the final plan, dated June 3, 1910, which was executed. The undated materials in folder C1D8F6 are of particular interest as these are the proposed plans of the house that differ quite significantly from what was built.
    - Proposed Alterations, James B. Duke House, Institute of Fine Arts, New York University, 1 E. 78th Street. Robert Venturi, architect. 1958. Ink.
      - Sub-Basement (Oversize-folder C1D8F1)
      - Ground Floor (Oversize-folder C1D8F1)
      - First Floor (Oversize-folder C1D8F1)
      - Second Floor (Oversize-folder C1D8F1)
      - Third Floor (Oversize-folder C1D8F1)
    - Residence of Mr. J.B. Duke, Fifth Ave. & 78th St., New York City. Horace Trumbauer, architect. July 1909. Blueprint; sepia diazo.
      - Sub-Basement Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F2)
      - Basement Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F2)
      - Basement Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F2)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F2)
      - Revised First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F2)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F2)
    - Residence of Mr. J.B. Duke, Fifth Ave. & 78th St., New York City. Horace Trumbauer, architect. July 1909. Blueprint; sepia diazo.
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
      - Second Floor Plan, Revised (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
      - Roof Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F3)
    - Residence of Mr. J.B. Duke, Fifth Ave. & 78th St., New York City. Horace Trumbauer, architect. July 1909. Blueprint; sepia diazo.
      - Fifth Ave. Elevation, 78th Street Elevation (Oversize-folder C1D8F4)
      - Fifth Ave. Elevation, 78th Street Elevation (Oversize-folder C1D8F4)
      - East Elevation, North Elevation (Oversize-folder C1D8F4)
      - East Elevation, North Elevation (Oversize-folder C1D8F4)
      - Cross Section, Longitudinal Section (Oversize-folder C1D8F4)
      - Typical Exterior Details (Oversize-folder C1D8F4)
    - Residence of Mr. J.B. Duke, Fifth Ave. & 78th St., New York City. Horace Trumbauer, architect. July 1909. Blueprint.
      - Basement Floor Framing Plan Showing Sub-Basement Walls (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - First Floor Framing Plan Showing Basement Story Walls (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Second Floor Framing Plan Showing First Story Walls (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Third Floor Framing Plan Showing Second Floor Walls (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Third Story Ceiling Framing Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Roof Framing Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Sub-Basement Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Basement Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Loft Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
      - Removable Bar for Ball Room at 1 E. 78 St. (H. Drewery Baker, designer) (Oversize-folder C1D8F5)
    - Proposed Residence of J.B. Duke, Fifth Ave. & 78th St. Horace Trumbauer, architect. undated. Gel lithograph, pencil, ink, and crayon, Vandyke print.
      - Basement Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Basement Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Fourth Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - First Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Second Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
      - Third Floor Plan (Oversize-folder C1D8F6)
    - Residence for Mr. George J. Gould, 5th Avenue and 67th St, New York City, Sheet No. 1-Ground Floor Plan, First Floor Plan, Sub Basement Plan, Basement Plan. Horace Trumbauer, architect. 1907 Mar 19. Blueline on vellum. (Oversize-folder NYA1)
    - Residence for Mr. George J. Gould, 5th Avenue and 67th St, New York City, Sheet No. 2-Fourth Floor Plan, Roof, Third Floor Plan, Second Floor Plan. Horace Trumbauer, architect. 1907 Mar 19. Blueline on vellum. (Oversize-folder NYA1)
    - Residence for Mr. George J. Gould, 5th Avenue and 67th St, New York City, Sheet No. 3-Elevation on Fifth Avenue, Elevation on 67th Street, Rear Elevation. 1907 Mar 19. Blueline on vellum. (Oversize-folder NYA1)
    - Residence for Mr. George J. Gould, 5th Avenue and 67th St, New York City, Sheet No. 4-Longitudinal Section, Party Wall Elevation. Horace Trumbauer, architect. 1907 Mar 19. Blueline on vellum. (Oversize-folder NYA1)
    - Wood cabinet for Capehart to be Lacquered. McMillen, Inc. 1944 May 22. Pencil on vellum. (Oversize-folder NYA2)
    - [Tentative sketches for Capehart Cabinet] (4 drawings). McMillen, Inc. [1944 May 4]. Diazo. (Oversize-folder NYA2)
    - Full Size Detail of Foot. McMillen, Inc. 1944 Jun 6. Blueprint. (Oversize-folder NYA2)
    - Laundry Room for the Residence of J.B. Duke. The American Laundry Machinery Co. 1922 Jan 22. Blueprint. (Oversize-folder NYA2)
    - [Survey of E. 78th and Fifth Avenue]. Geo. C. Hollwirth. 1908 Dec 15. Blueprint. (Oversize-folder NYA2)
    - [Design of Panels for New York Apartment]. Includes fabric samples. Eliseo J. Lisi, interior designer. 1980. Ink. (Oversize-folder NYA3)
- New York Apartment (3 E. 84th Street, Penthouse), 1941-1967
  Purchased by Doris Duke in June 1952, this New York apartment boasted 5 bedrooms, 3 baths, 2 master bedrooms and a terrace surrounding the apartment with private hedges. When the lease expired in September 1967, Doris Duke transferred the stock (as it was a co-operative apartment building) and proprietary lease to New York University in November of the same year.
  - Administrative Records, 1941-1967
    Materials in the sub series include the original lease and later transfer of the apartment, invoices and receipts for repairs and renovations to the apartment, and correspondence and memoranda relating to routine matters of the apartment including expenses and inventory.
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to routine matters including NY Apartment expenses and a few invoices from McMillen Inc. for work orders. 1952–1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Doris Duke’s Penthouse Apartment at 3 E. 84th Street (1952–1967). Doris Duke donated this co-op to N.Y.U. on November 20, 1967. Closing statement included in file. 1964–1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Invoices and estimates for work on furnishings at 3 E. 84th Street. 1941–1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Invoices and statements for purchases made from McMillen Inc. for 3 E. 84th Street. 1952–1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Invoices for furniture and fixtures purchased for 3 E. 84th Street. 1952–1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Estimates for alterations to the New York Apartment, 3 E. 84th Street, from McMillen Inc. Includes tax Assessment for property. 1952–1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Estimate from McMillen, Inc. for two pairs of curtains for Doris Duke’s Dressing Room in her New York Apartment, 3 E. 84th Street. December 27, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Financial statements of 3 E. 84th Street Corporation. 1954–1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Invoices relating to the installation of audio equipment at 3 E. 84th Street. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Invoices from Ernest Treganowan, Inc. for needlepoint. 1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Invoice for repairs of silk, Shantung, Living Room curtains at 3 E. 84th Street Apartment by Burrows Interiors. 1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Proprietary Lease with 3 E. 84th Street as lessor. c. 1940s (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Agreement between Raymond P. Sloan (seller) and Doris Duke (purchaser) for 3 E. 84th Street Penthouse for $22,000. June 5, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Meeting notices to the stockholders a 3 E. 84th Street Corporation. 1953–1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Acceptance of Assignment and Assumption of Lease between Doris Duke and New York University (assignee) for 3 E. 84th Street, PH, on November 20, 1967. File also includes letter to Doris Duke from N.Y.U. confirming the transfer of the Proprietary Lease to N.Y.U. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Annual Reports, 3 E. 84th Street. 1951–1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Inventory of furnishings at 3 E. 84th Street. 1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- New York Apartment (475 Park Avenue, Penthouse B), 1965-1997
  The Penthouse B apartment at 475 Park Avenue was purchased by Doris Duke in July 1965. At the time it was described as a "dream" apartment with seven rooms, 4 bathrooms, 13 closets and a wood-burning fireplace. It was surrounded by a 1,000 square foot veranda facing E. 58th Street. The apartment was renovated several times including during the mid-1960s by architect Gerhard Karplus and designer Tony Duquette. After the death of Miss Duke, the apartment was sold by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in 1997.
  - Administrative Records, 1965-1997
    Topics in this sub series primarily center on renovations, repairs, general up-keep, and furniture and fixtures purchased for the 475 Park Avenue apartment. Materials include invoices, vouchers, bills and correspondence concerning work and daily operations of the NY apartment, and general meeting notices and financial statements for the shareholders of the 475 Park Avenue Corporation. Of particular interest are the correspondence and invoices related to the interior design work to the apartment by designer Tony Duquette.
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to alterations performed at the NY Apartment. 1965–1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily operations at the NY Apartment including the installation of an alarm system. 1965–1969, 1978, 1982–1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily operations of DBO and Doris Duke in relation to activities at the NY Apartment. 1981–1984, 1989–1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily operations and routine matters concerning the NY Apartment. 1983–1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and related materials concerning zoning and permits needed for alterations to the NY Apartment. 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Memoranda relating to the cleaning and repair of a bronze statue located at the NY Apartment. 1992 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to maintenance at the NY Apartment. 1992–1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda relating to the repair of a tiger skin rug. 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to daily operations of the DBO and Bernard Lafferty in relation to the NY Apartment. 1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and memoranda relating to the transfer of furnishings from the NY Apartment to Somerville and work conducted at the NY Apartment. 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence relating to maintenance of the NY Apartment. 1996–1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Copies of invoices of furniture and fixtures purchased for the 475 Park Ave., PH-B, and E. 84th St Apartments. File also includes invoices for purchases for the 1 E. 78th St. mansion and Duke Farms. 1939, 1942–1976 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Invoice for purchase of a barber bottle from the Parke-Bernet Galleries. Includes photographs of a candelabra. c. 1950s, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Invoices and related materials concerning construction and alterations to the NY Apartment. 1966–1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Invoices and vouchers for contractor’s work at the NY Apartment. 1966, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Invoices and vouchers relating to expenses and daily operations at the NY Apartment. 1967–1968, 1978–1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Invoices relating to plumbing needs at the NY Apartment. 1967, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Invoices, bills, and related correspondence concerning work and daily operations at the NY Apartment. 1967–1972, 1980–1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)